→ 通往ISS的旅途
第二部分：联盟飞船交会对接
我是Alexander Gerst ESA的宇航员
I am Alexander Gerst an astronaut of the European Space Agency.
亚历山大·格斯特
欧空局宇航员
我现在在国际空间站和你们说话
I am talking to you from the International Space Station.
我到这里的旅程从登上联盟号飞船开始
My journey here aboard a Soyuz spacecraft
字幕翻译/压制：NeXT-X6，旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/M2_NeFbFcSw
原视频发布日期：20141121
原作者名：European Space Agency, ESA
从哈萨克斯坦起飞到对接完成差不多花了5小时
from lift-off in Kazakhstan to the time we docked just took over about 5 hours.
接下来的视频会包含一些入轨后飞船内部拍摄的片段
The video you are about to see contains some unique footage taken inside the capsule while it is in orbit
视频也会解释联盟号如何安全入轨以及与对接国际空间站对接
and explains how the Soyuz safely reaches orbit and docks to the Space Station.
其他很多宇航员也经历了相同的旅程
Many other astronauts have taken the same journey
他们也会在这个视频里分享他们的经历
and some of them will also share their experience with you in this video.
看得开心:)
Have fun watching it.
9分钟前 联盟号飞船从哈萨克斯坦的拜科努尔发射场起飞进入轨道
Nine minutes ago, a Soyuz spacecraft blasted into orbit from Baikonur in Kazakhstan.
它现在绕着地球飞行 速度是喷气飞机的30倍
It is now speeding around the Earth thirty times faster than a jumbo jet.
它只有一个目标 追上
It has a single purpose: to catch up with,
并交会对接 离地400km某处的国际空间站
rendezvous, and dock with the International Space Station located somewhere 400 km above the ground.
宇航员刚刚完成了发射时序的最后一步
The astronauts just went through the last phase of the launch sequence
联盟号飞船与火箭的分离
the separation of the Soyuz spacecraft from the rocket.
发动机关机的动静相当大
The finishing of the engine of the shut-down of the engine is pretty strong.
保罗·内斯波利
欧空局宇航员
之后立刻 当然了 你漂浮起来
And immediately afterwards, of course, you float.
你知道 这真的是一种非常好的感觉 是的 我们在太空中 我们发射成功了
It's really a very nice feeling that you know yes, we are in space, we had a successful launch,
弗兰克·德·温纳
欧空局宇航员
现在我们在去空间站的路上
now we are on the way to the Space Station.
你可以看看窗外
You can look outside the window,
你第一次从上空看见地球壮丽的景象
you see this magnificent Earth for the first time from above.
这种感觉相当好
It's really a great feeling.
然后 绝美的太阳很快就出现了 照亮 迸发出光辉
And then just the absolute beauty of the sun coming up really quickly, illuminating, bursting into flame.
卢卡·帕尔米塔诺
欧空局宇航员
现在 他们首次进入环地轨道 进入高度约220公里
Now in their first orbits around Earth at an insertion altitude of about 220 km,
联盟号上的三名宇航员当然有着绝妙的视野
the three astronauts in the Soyuz certainly have a wonderful view.
但是还有工作要做
But there is work to be done,
因为他们离国际空间站还有几百公里的距离 他们的最终目的地
as they are still hundreds of kilometres away from the ISS -- their final destination.
国际空间站于1998年开始运行
The International Space Station began life in 1998
此后大约每90分钟绕地球运行一次
and has been orbiting Earth about once every 90 minutes ever since.
国际空间站的轨道平面是相当固定的
The orbital plane of the ISS is fairly constant,
而地球总是在自转
while the Earth is always rotating.
把国际空间站的轨道投影到二维地图上
Projecting the orbit of the ISS onto a 2D map,
我们可以看到一系列相交的曲线
we see a series of intersecting curves.
莫斯科和休斯敦的任务控制中心不断监测国际空间站的位置
The Mission Control Centres in Moscow and Houston constantly monitor the position of the ISS,
任务控制中心
俄罗斯，莫斯科
并能预测未来任何特定时间内国际空间站在轨道上的预期位置
and can predict its expected location in the orbit for any given time in the future.
任务控制中心
德州，休斯顿
这对于确定联盟号航天器何时发射具有重要意义
This is important for determining when the Soyuz spacecraft launches.
虽然在技术上可以在任何时候发射联盟号火箭
While it is technically possible to launch the Soyuz rocket at any time,
但在ISS轨道经过哈萨克斯坦的拜科努尔航天发射场后不久 进行发射的效率最高
it's most efficient to do so shortly after the ISS orbit passes over the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakhstan.
这就缩短了与空间站交会对接的时间
This shortens the amount of time to rendezvous and dock with the Station
从两天左右缩短到6个小时
from about two days to only six hours.
这种短时交会轨道自2013年开始实施
This short rendezvous trajectory has been implemented since 2013.
然而 如果联盟号火箭错过了必要的发射窗口
However, if the Soyuz rocket misses the necessary launch window
或接下来任何的发动机点火不能按计划进行
or any of the upcoming engine burns do not occur as planned,
航天器有足够的多余燃料 可以恢复到两天的长时交会对接
the spacecraft has enough extra fuel to revert to a two-day long rendezvous.
这发生在2014年3月 由于高度控制问题
This happened in March of 2014 because of an attitude control problem,
第39远征队
交会被重新规划为过去使用的长时轨道
and thus, the rendezvous was replanned to the formerly used long trajectory.
你要考虑到这有一定的风险
You take into consideration that there are some risks,
有的风险比其他的更严重
some are worse than others,
包括从快速对接过渡到长时对接的可能性
including the possibility of transitioning from a very short docking to a long docking,
短对接：5-6小时
长对接：2天
这是一年前的标准
which was the standard until a year ago.
我们知道这种可能性 这是我们为之训练的东西
We know of the possibility; it's something that we are trained for.
我们知道航天器上有我们这两天所需要的一切
We know that the spacecraft has everything that we need for those two days,
我们也知道如何应对
and we know how to react.
交会的定义是
Rendezvous is defined
两个空间飞行器相互接近的一系列机动动作
as the sequence of manoeuvres governing the approach of two space vehicles to one another.
在大多数情况下 其中一个是追逐者 执行机动 在这种情况下 是联盟号
In most cases one of them is the chaser, performing the manoeuvres, in this case, the Soyuz,
而第二个是被动目标飞行器 在这种情况下是国际空间站
while the second is a passive target vehicle, in this case, the International Space Station.
理想情况下，两个飞行器在预选的空间和时间上准确安全地相遇
Ideally, both vehicles meet up safely at an exact preselected point in space and time.
但联盟号是如何实现的呢？
But how does the Soyuz achieve this?
联盟号必须从最初的进入高度爬升
Well, the Soyuz has to climb from its initial insertion altitude
联盟飞船高度：220km
到与空间站相同的高度 然后进入并停留在这个轨道上
up to the same altitude of the Station, and then join and stay on this orbit.
空间站高度：420km
这听起来是一个足够简单的任务
It sounds like a simple enough task,
但这不可能从开始的进入高度 只用一次机动就完成
but it cannot be done in one single manoeuvre starting from the insertion altitude.
最终对接的计算是基于联盟号精确的初始高度的
Calculations for the final docking are based on a precise initial Soyuz altitude
遗憾的是 我们事先不知道确切的进入轨道高度
and unfortunately, the exact insertion orbit altitude is not known in advance
这是由于火箭发射过程中存在一些不可预测性
because of some unpredictability in the rocket launch.
因此 会使用两次机动的方式 其间有一个中间调相轨道
Therefore, two manoeuvres are used with an intermediate phasing orbit in between.
相位调整轨道是最终对接计算的基础
The phasing orbit is the basis for the final docking calculations.
它是用第一种机动的方式到达的 称为霍曼转移
It is reached using the first manoeuvre, called a Hohmann transfer,
瓦尔特·霍曼
德国科学家
即以20世纪初一位德国科学家的名字命名的
named after a German scientist from the beginning of the 20th century.
在霍曼转移过程中 联盟号要使用两次发动机
During the Hohmann transfer, the Soyuz has to use its engines twice.
第一次是在发射后不久离开目前的进入轨道
The first time is to leave its current insertion orbit shortly after launch
并上升转移到调相轨道上
and transfer up to the phasing orbit.
第二次是让飞行器以适当的速度飞行 使其保持在那个轨道上
The second time is to get the vehicle traveling at the right speed to stay on that orbit.
调相轨道比国际空间站轨道低100公里左右 它的作用非常特殊
The phasing orbit is lower than the ISS orbit by about 100 km and it serves a very specific purpose.
它减少了相位角 或者说两个航天器在各自轨道上的相位角
It decreases the phasing angle, or the angle between the two spacecraft in their respective orbits.
这里我们看到联盟号在相位调整轨道上运行 用黄色的颜色标明
Here we see the Soyuz orbiting in the phasing orbit, depicted in yellow,
而国际空间站在更高的轨道上运行 用绿色标明
while the ISS is orbiting in a higher orbit, depicted in green.
第三个红色轨道是联盟号已经离开的进入轨道
The third red orbit is the insertion orbit the Soyuz has already left.
由于联盟号在较低的轨道上 它的飞行速度会比空间站快
Because the Soyuz is on a lower orbit it will travel faster than the Station.
因此 联盟号利用这个调相轨道追赶国际空间站
Therefore, the Soyuz uses this phasing orbit to catch up with the ISS.
根据使用的是长时交会还是短时交会
Depending on whether the long or short rendezvous approach is being used,
联盟号将在这个调相轨道上停留近两天或仅仅几个小时
the Soyuz will remain in this phasing orbit for close to two days, or just a few hours,
无论达到所需的相位角需要多长时间
however long it takes to reach the desired phasing angle.
同一时间 宇航员还不只是享受美景和失重
Meanwhile, the crew haven't just been enjoying the views and weightlessness,
他们一直在忙着查漏补缺 确保系统正常运行
they've been busy with leak checks and making sure systems are performing nominally.
然后他们发出对接探针伸出的命令
Then they issue the command for docking probe extension
为最后的对接时序做提前准备
in advanced preparation for the final docking sequence.
只要确认了飞船的气压完好
As soon as the pressure integrity of the vehicle is confirmed,
任务控制中心就会发出指令 让宇航员松开安全带
the Mission Control Centre gives the go-ahead for the crew to loosen their seatbelts,
打开头盔 脱掉手套
open their helmets, and take off their gloves.
到达调相轨道后
Once they reach the phasing orbit,
宇航员们终于有了一些应得的休息时间
the crew finally have some well-deserved downtime,
特别是那些完成了为期两天的长时交会的人
especially those completing the two-day long rendezvous trajectory.
我们所说的五个耳聋轨道
There are what we call five deaf orbits.
长交会
这是5个其上宇航员不能与地面联系的轨道
It's five orbits in which the crew cannot have contact with the ground
这是因为联盟号飞船的轨道没有经过俄罗斯的上空
because the orbit of the Soyuz is not passing over Russia,
只有当你与联盟号经过俄罗斯上空时 你才能与地面接触
and you only have contact with the ground when you're passing over Russia with the Soyuz.
所以你只能完全靠自己
So you are completely on yourself.
所以对于宇航员来说 这其实是个很不错的时候 因为你不会被打扰
So it's actually a nice time for the crew, because you cannot be disturbed,
没有人能给你任务 你想做什么就做什么
nobody can give you tasks, you can do whatever you want.
幸运的是 对宇航员来说
Luckily for the astronauts,
联盟号的设计让他们在整个旅程中不用被限制在座位上
the Soyuz is designed so they are not confined to their seats for the entire trip.
联盟号虽然小 但可以让宇航员在可进入的舱室之间自由移动
Though small, the spacecraft allows the astronauts to move freely between the accessible modules.
联盟号有三个舱段 轨道舱
The Soyuz has three compartments: the Orbital Module,
返回舱 以及设备舱
the Descent Module, and the Instrument Compartment.
每个舱段都有不同的结构 也有特定的用途
Each compartment has a different architecture, and a specific purpose.
轨道舱 也就是生活舱
The Orbital Module, or living compartment,
配有睡袋 食物和厕所
is equipped with sleeping bags, food, and a toilet.
现在我们在联盟号上
So here we are in the Soyuz.
在一个对接好的联盟飞船里
这就是我们所说的БО 生活舱 俄语中的бытовой отсек
This is what we call the БО, the living compartment, "бытовой отсек" in Russian.
苏妮塔·威廉斯
NASA宇航员
它还有一个小浴室 只是没有其他的浴室那么好
It also has a little bathroom, it's not as good as the other bathrooms
所以我们尽可能不去使用它
so we try not to use it too much.
b23.tv/av12593669 26:00
youtube上的原视频我没找到……
这里面有饮用水 如果我们需要喝水的话
It has drinking water in it if we need something to drink,
然后当然 它为我们装了很多货物
and then, of course, it's filled up with a lot of cargo for us.
设备舱 宇航员无法进入
The Instrument Compartment, not accessible to the astronauts,
里面有氧气罐和推进剂罐
houses the oxygen and propellant tanks,
推进器 机载计算机和一些传感器
thrusters, the on-board computer, and a number of sensors.
从返回舱中
From the Descent Module,
三名宇航员监控着有关航天器和国际空间站的所有信息
the three crewmembers monitor all information about the spacecraft and the ISS
包括地面数据 机载计算机
from ground data, the on-board computers,
以及一个安装在外部的潜望镜的光学视角
and an optical display of the view from a periscope mounted on the outside.
在第二次轨道转移和最后的交会对接中
For the second orbital transfer and the final rendezvous manoeuvres,
宇航员返回到这个舱内的座位上
the astronauts return to their seats in this module.
第二次轨道转移将联盟号从调相轨道上升到国际空间站轨道
The second orbital transfer brings the Soyuz from the phasing orbit up to the ISS orbit.
这就是双椭圆转移 需要三次发动机点火 而不是霍曼转移的两次
It's called a bielliptic transfer, and requires three engine burns instead of the Hohmann's two.
从调相轨道出发 前两次点火将联盟号送上国际空间站轨道
From the phasing orbit, the first two burns bring the Soyuz up to the ISS orbit.
第三次点火使飞行器以正确的速度 在国际空间站轨道上停留
The third burn gets the vehicle traveling at the correct speed to stay in the ISS orbit.
双椭圆转移的点火是根据调相轨道的精确高度来计算的
The burns of the bielliptic transfer are calculated based on the precise altitude of the phasing orbit.
因此 如果调相轨道过高或过低的话
And consequently, if the phasing orbit is too high or too low
联盟号不会像预期的那样与国际空间站交会
the Soyuz will not meet up with the ISS as expected.
这里用双椭圆转移而不是霍曼转移的原因是
The reason for using a bielliptic transfer here instead of the Hohmann's is
联盟号不仅可以在国际空间站附近达到正确的高度
that the Soyuz will not only reach the correct altitude in the close vicinity of the ISS,
还能以准确的速度到达国际空间站
but also with exactly the desired speed.
尽管有这些精确的机动
Despite these precise manoeuvres,
但如果推进器未能使联盟号减速
what if the thrusters fail to slow down the Soyuz
而它在接近国际空间站时飞行速度过快怎么办？
and the vehicle travels too fast as it approaches the ISS?
这可能是个灾难性的结局 联盟号不是对接 而是撞上了空间站
This could end in disaster, with the Soyuz crashing into the Station instead of docking.
为了防止这种情况的发生 联盟号进行了一次额外的侧向点火
To prevent this from happening the Soyuz performs an additional side burn.
这样一来 它的轨道平面稍有变化 两飞行器之间就不可能发生碰撞
This changes its orbital plane slightly and makes a collision between the two vehicles impossible.
在整个交会对接过程中
Throughout the rendezvous process,
联盟号机载计算机不断确定联盟号本身和国际空间站的位置和速度
the Soyuz on-board computer continually determines the position and velocity of the Soyuz itself and of the ISS.
为此 它使用地面测控提供的测量结果
To do so, it uses measurements provided by the ground controllers
和一个叫Kurs的雷达系统
and a radar system called the Kurs.
这样一来
In this way,
交会期间的所有点火都由机载计算机计算并自动完成
all of the burns during the rendezvous are calculated and automated by the on-board computer.
联盟号使用特殊的雷达系统在太空中导航并寻找空间站
So Soyuz navigates in space and looks for the Station with a special radar system,
这个系统叫做Kurs
which is called the Kurs.
这在离空间站400km的地方就会被打开
This gets turned on at 400 km from the Station.
它找啊找啊找
It looks, looks, looks,
一般情况下 会在180公里左右看见并锁定空间站
and usually it sees the Station and locks into the Station at around, more or less, 180 kilometres.
在这个距离 我们事实上看不到空间站
At that distance, we really don't see the Station.
它可能 即使你能看到它 它可能和太空中的任何一颗恒星都很相似
It's probably -- even if you could see it, it's probably similar to any of the stars that are up there in space.
但你在屏幕上看到 那个锁定标志 软件显示雷达锁定了空间站
But you see on the screen the lock, the software indication that the radar locked into the Station.
联盟飞船显示器
锁定
前面提到的双椭圆转移的第三次也是最后一次点火是非常重要的
The third and final burn of the pre-mentioned bielliptic transfer is very important,
因为它为飞行器对接前的近ISS交会程序做好了准备
because it sets the vehicle up for its near-ISS rendezvous procedures that will lead to docking.
当你正常点火时
When you do a normal burn,
飞行器以每秒两度的速度旋转到正确的姿态
the vehicle rotates to the correct attitude at two degrees per second,
然后大约8分钟后开始点火
and then it takes about eight minutes to start the burn.
当你接近空间站时 你必须要减速
When you're close to the Space Station and you have to brake,
当然这样是不行的
of course this would not work.
所以飞行器突然间开始快速旋转
So then the vehicle all of a sudden starts rotating quite fast,
一秒三度半 紧接着
three and a half degrees per second and only just after that,
50秒之后 你就已经开始点火
50 seconds after that you already have the burn.
而一旦点火完成后
And once the burn is completed,
飞行器立即又开始向正常方向旋转
immediately the vehicle starts rotating again to the normal orientation,
宇航员必须对此进行相当严格的监控
and the crew has to monitor this quite intensely
去看一切是否正常真的是工作量的高峰
and these are really high peaks of workload to see that everything is okay,
旋转还算顺利
the rotation is going okay,
你知道你点火了 点火数值没问题
you know that you have the burn, the burn values were okay,
你旋转回去 然后在你的主显示屏上看到空间站
you rotate back, and then you see back the Space Station in your main display.
我们可以看到 先是一个点 比天空中的其他星星亮了一点
We could see it, first a dot a little bit brighter than the other stars in the sky,
然后一点一点地
and then little by little,
我们开始看到像小蜘蛛一样的 那些太阳能阵列和其他所有东西
we start to see like a little spider first with all the solar arrays and everything,
然后很清楚地 有个巨大的物体出现在我们眼前
and then it was apparent that there's a huge outpost right there in front of us.
在这个阶段 坐在中间的指令长
During this stage, the crew commander, sitting in the middle
向同伴发布重要信息和指令
gives vital information and instructions to his crewmates.
他们的工作量增加了 许多参数需要检查 许多系统需要激活
Their workload has increased; many parameters need to be checked and systems activated.
发射前几天
Days before launch,
莫斯科和休斯顿飞行任务控制中心的飞行动力学专家小组
a team of flight dynamics experts at the Mission Control Centres in Moscow and Houston
确定了国际空间站的理想位置和方向
determine the ideal position and orientation of the ISS,
基于对制约因素的仔细分析
based on a careful analysis of the constraints
这些因素可能会影响交会对接时间线上的最后步骤
that could affect these final stages of the rendezvous timeline.
首先 对接时必须有足够的照明条件
First, there must be adequate lighting conditions at the time of docking
这样 联盟号上的宇航员就可以看到国际空间站 而不会由于太阳而暂时失明或被遮挡
so that the Soyuz crew can see the ISS without being blinded or blocked by the sun.
（战雷梗）安东核弹太阳
要看空间站是否有光照 是否在阳光下
It depends if the Station is illuminated, is in the sun,
那么即使距离相对较远也能看到它
then you can see it even if you are relatively far away.
但是 如果空间站不在阳光下 那么即使离得再近也看不到它
But if the Station is not in the sun, then you cannot see it even if you are close.
此外 必须避免ISS部件过大的温度波动
Additionally, major temperature fluctuations of ISS elements,
如太阳能阵列等 以防止结构变形
such as the solar arrays, must be avoided to prevent structural deformation.
最后 地面 联盟号和国际空间站之间必须有通畅的通信线路
Finally, there must be clear communication pathways between the ground, Soyuz, and ISS.
交会是由机载计算机执行的一个完全自动化的过程
The rendezvous is a fully automated process performed by the on-board computer.
但是 指令长仍旧拿着手动控制器
However, the commander still takes the hand controller
以防万一需要进行应急手动对接
just in case there is a need to perform a contingency manual docking.
如果你没有看到空间站 或者在那一刻发生了什么事情
If you don't see the Space Station or something happens at that moment,
那么你可能就需要手动控制了
then you might have to take manual control.
所以你要牢牢记住空间站现在在哪里
And so you have to remember very well, where is the Space Station now,
我要采取什么行动
what are the actions that I'm going to take,
这才是真正的紧张时刻
and this is really the intense moments that happen.
手动对接需要两个手动控制器来驾驶飞行器
Manual docking requires two hand controllers to pilot the vehicle,
左边的控制平移 右边的控制旋转
a left one that control translation and a right one that controls rotation.
航天员们都经过了彻底的手动对接培训
The crew are thoroughly trained in these manual docking procedures,
甚至在拜科努尔的发射前最后几天都会进行练习
even training until the very last days before launch in Baikonur.
除了应急对接
Besides contingency docking,
宇航员们还可以将他们的手动控制训练应用在重新对接的机动中
the crew might also utilize their manual control training during redocking manoeuvres.
国际空间站不断有载人的联盟号飞船和其他无人驾驶的补给飞船到来
The ISS is constantly visited by manned Soyuz vehicles and other unmanned supply ships.
这里出现的是ATV（Automated Transfer Vehicle），
欧空局研制的货运飞船，使用和进步飞船一样的对接标准，
用于对接俄罗斯舱段
有时需要将对接的的联盟号分离
Sometimes it is necessary to undock an attached Soyuz
将其重新停靠到国际空间站的另一个对接口 为新飞船腾出空间
and redock it to another port on the ISS to make room for one of these new ships.
Luca Parmitano 在第37远征队任务中做了此事
Luca Parmitano did this as part of Expedition 37.
我的队员是为数不多能进行人工对接的宇航员之一 整个对接过程非常顺利
My crew was one of the few crews able to perform a manual docking and it went very smoothly.
我们很兴奋 因为这是我们训练了很久的东西 而且我们有能力做到这一点
We were excited because it's something that we trained on for a long time and we were able to do it.
除了这种情况外 常规的对接程序是全自动的
Apart from this case, a routine docking sequence is fully automated
宇航员的主要任务是监控系统 确保程序正常运行
and the crew's main task is to monitor the systems to ensure nominal procedures.
在这个常规对接过程的阶段中 飞行器的相对速度不断降低
At this stage during routine docking the vehicle's relative speed continues to decrease,
两者之间的距离也会不断缩短
as does the distance between the two.
在距离空间站400米的地方 新的阶段开始了
400 metres from the Space Station, a new phase enters.
联盟飞船显示器
绕飞
这就是我们所说的绕飞阶段
This is the phase what we call fly-around.
在这个阶段 飞行器实际上并没有对准所需的对接端口
During this phase, the vehicle is actually not pointing at the desired docking port,
而是对准了空间站的任意一个Kurs天线
but at either one of the Station's Kurs antennas.
只有当飞行器到达150米的位置保持模式时
It's only when the vehicle reaches its 150m station keeping mode
方向才会改变为指向所选的对接端口
that the orientation changes to point at the selected docking port instead.
然后联盟号进行第二次绕飞 对准对接端口
The Soyuz then performs a second fly-around to align up with the docking port
同时保持150米的距离
while keeping a distance of 150 m.
一旦对准了对接端口
Once aligned with the docking port,
宇航员发出最后一个阶段的指令 最后进近
the crew issues the command for the last stage: the final approach.
联盟号计算机显示器利用Kurs的数据为航天员提供
The Soyuz computer display uses data from Kurs to provide the astronauts
联盟飞船显示器（已加速）
有关交会对接的相关信息
with pertinent information about the rendezvous and docking manoeuvres.
在其他读数中 与国际空间站的距离有被显示
Among other read-outs, the distance from the ISS is displayed,
这里显示的是5m
here showing five metres,
而在接近过程中的相对速度也是如此
as is the relative velocity during the approach,
现在显示的是10cm/s.
currently 10 cm/s.
这些信息和其他信息会叠加在视频源上
This and other information is overlaid on the video feed,
用于跟踪目标的对齐
used to track alignment of the target.
一旦探针碰到对接舱门的入口锥体 就会发生接触
Contact occurs as soon as the probe touches the entrance cone of the docking hatch.
然后推进器给了联盟号一个额外的推动力
Then the thrusters give the Soyuz an extra push,
对接机构确保了捕获
and the docking mechanism ensures capture.
接触
捕获
我想这就是碰撞的地方
I think this is where the impact was.
所以我觉得是偏离中心4到5英寸左右
So I would say about four to five inches off-centre.
对于经过了几百万英里来说相当不错
Pretty good after traveling for a couple million miles!
探针缩回 两架飞行器就会更架接近对方
The probe retracts, and you get the two vehicles closer to each other,
然后当它们之间的距离很近的时候
and then when they are very close to each other,
不到两三毫米 钩子就开始合拢
less than two to three millimetres, the hooks start closing.
而当这些钩子完全闭合时 就会承受巨大的压力
And it's when these hooks are fully closed that can take an enormous pressure
因为每一个钩子可以承受16吨的力
because they can withstand 16 tonnes of force, each of the hooks,
而你在联盟号飞船上有8个钩子
and you have eight hooks on the Soyuz vehicle.
这样做还是不够 因为O型环里面可能会有东西
This is still not enough, because there might be something inside the O-rings,
一些污垢或者是一些杂物 这些都会使密封性不好
some dirt or some debris, that is not allowing for a good seal.
所以会高精度地进行一系列相应的真空和减压的工作
So there is a series of vacuum and depressurisations done in a very astute manner
可以验证每一个隔间是否真的密封严密
that verifies that each one of these compartments is actually sealed tight.
只有在这时 顺便说一下 这一切都需要一个小时 一到两个小时
Only at that point -- and by the way, all of this takes I would say an hour, one to two hours.
只有当一切都被证明是完全密封的时候
Only then when everything is proved to be fully sealed,
只有这样 你才能打开空间站的舱门 联盟号的舱门
only then you can open the hatch of the Station, the hatch of the Soyuz,
宇航员们才能真正进入太空站
and the crew can actually go into the Station.
我们通常要做的就是敲空间站一侧的舱门
And what we usually do is we knock on the hatch that goes on the side of the Space Station,
他们敲回来 我们知道那边有人
they knock back; we know that there is somebody else on the other side
而联盟号飞船和国际空间站之间的舱门
And the hatches between the Soyuz spacecraft and the International Space Station
在中央时间11点14分开放
opening at 11:14 PM Central Time.
然后是大家的拥抱和微笑
Then it's hugs and smiles for everybody.
宇航员们现在安全地登上了国际空间站
The astronauts are now safely on-board the International Space Station,
他们未来6个月的家
their home for the next six months.